Guide to the Methodist Episcopal Hospital reports and publications ARC.155
Brooklyn Historical Society
Methodist Episcopal Hospital reports and publications
1888-1992
Brooklyn Historical Society
Methodist Hospital School of Nursing (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
ARC.155
2 Linear Feet in four manuscript boxes
The Methodist Episcopal Hospital reports and publications contains annual reports and assorted publications produced by the Methodist Episcopal Hospital in Park Slope from 1888-1992.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The source and date of acquisition for the majority of this collection are unknown. The nursing school yearbooks and two other items were a transfer from the hospital in 2024 and 2025 (CBH accession 2024.036).
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into four series by type: Series 1: Reports and administrative documents, Series 2: Publications and ephemera, and Series 3: School of Nursing yearbooks. Within each series, materials are arranged chronologically.
Historical note
In 1881, the Reverend James Monroe Buckley, editor of the periodical The Christian Advocate, made an appeal to the publication's Methodist readership to contribute to the establishment of a new hospital that would help to address the health concerns of Brooklyn's rapidly growing population. Buckley's appeal was answered by prominent banker George Ingraham Seney, who contributed $100,000 and several plots of land to begin construction of the hospital, and to incorporate the institution. The hospital was incorporated on May 27, 1881, and opened on December 19, 1887 at the corner of 6th Street and 7th Avenue in the Park Slope neighborhood of Brooklyn. Originally housed in three buildings with a staff of 16, Methodist Episcopal Hospital grew steadily throughout the 20th century, and as of 2023 it comprises a sprawling complex of buildings with a staff of several hundred. In the 1990s, the institution's name was officially changed to New York Methodist Hospital, and in 2016, its name changed again to NewYork-Presbyterian Brooklyn Methodist Hospital when it became part of the NewYork–Presbyterian Healthcare System network.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
If digital surrogates exist, they should be used in place of the originals whenever possible.
Related Materials
There is information about the hospital's development in the Ronald Shiffman collection on the Pratt Center for Community Development (2013.023)
Edwin Warriner Papers and Photographs, 1790-1958 (1977.255)
Records of the Brooklyn Council for Social Planning (BCMS.0039)
Brooklyn ephemera collection (BCMS.0007)
Brooklyn Historical Society ephemera collection (ARC.272)
Brooklyn neighborhood associations and civic organizations publications (ARC.167)
Scope and Contents
The Methodist Episcopal Hospital reports and publications date from 1888 to 1992 and primarily consist of the hospital's annual reports. Included in the collection are a complete run of annual reports from 1888 to 1962, and scattered annual reports dated 1964 to 1990. These documents feature summaries of the hospital's activities and accomplishments for each year, the names of donors and donations made, as well as summaries of the hospital's financial standing for each year. The collection also includes three programs for 1960s events benefitting the hospital, copies of its charter and bylaws dated 1888, 1897, and 1905, and several hospital publications: Methodist Hospital News, Heartbeat, and Today.
In addition, the collection includes several yearbook's from the hospital's nursing school, for various years between 1925 and 1963.
Hospitals -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Annual reports; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Park Slope (New York, N.Y.); Programs (documents); Newsletters; Nursing schools -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Hospitals -- Medical staff -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Medical care -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Methodist Hospital School of Nursing (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Series 1: Reports and administrative documents
  - Guidance of architects in preparing designs for the Methodist Episcopal Hospital, 1881 (Box 2)
  - Annual reports, 1888-1928 (Box 1)
  - Charter and By-Laws, 1888, 1897, 1905 (Box 2)
  - Superintendents report, 1892, 1907 (Box 2)
  - Fundraising letter and circular, 1898 (Box 2)
  - Annual reports, 1928-1962, 1964-1969, 1971, 1980, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Park Slope Civic Council letter regarding new hospital building, 1988 (Box 2)
- Series 2: Publications and ephemera
  - Methodist Hospital News, 1936-1937 (Box 2)
  - Heartbeat, Sept. 1958, 1960-1962 (Box 2)
  - Florence Nightingale Federation annual bazaar programs, 1962, 1966, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Today, 1990-1992 (Box 2)
- Series 3: School of Nursing yearbooks
  - Agrypnotic yearbook, 1925-1927, 1931, 1941 (Box 3)
  - Mehsonib yearbook, 1938 (Box 3)
  - The Lamp yearbook, 1940 (Box 3)
  - Crossroads yearbook, 1943 (Box 3)
  - Bricks and Ivy yearbook, 1944 (Box 3)
  - Triumph yearbook, 1956-1957 (Box 3)
  - Elohim yearbook, 1958 (Box 4)
  - Pathways yearbook, 1959 (Box 4)
  - Horizons yearbook, 1962-1963 (Box 4)